<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="en">DEPCHA - Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative for Historical
					Accounts</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher xml:lang="de">Karl-Franzens-Universität Graz</publisher>
				<publisher xml:lang="en">University of Graz</publisher>
				<date when="2023">2023</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl/>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p/>
			</projectDesc>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation> <date when="2023">2023</date> <name type="place">Graz, Austria</name> </creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="header">
				<head>DEPCHA - Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative for Historical Accounts</head>
			</div>
			<div>
				<div type="body">
					<p>The DEPCHA (Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative for Historical Accounts)
						project uses Semantic Web technologies to present diverse financial data
						from historical documents on a web-based platform. The project's goal goes
						beyond data sharing and long-term preservation, focusing on the development
						of a web interface with exploration, visualisation and self-organisation
						features. DEPCHA serves as a discovery and publication hub for datasets and
						digital editions of historical financial documents, adhering to the FAIR
						data principles. The initiative relies on GAMS, a Humanities Asset
						Management System providing research data infrastructure, maintained by the
						Centre for Information Modelling at the University of Graz. DEPCHA combines
						digital editions functionalities with Semantic Web and Linked Open Data
						concepts to create a knowledge graph detailing the different contexts and
						research foci of the source. An interactive user interface is designed to
						explore and analyse entities and data from historical sources. A faceted
						analytical display, also known as a dashboard, uses information
						visualisation to present different perspectives and use cases.</p>
					<div>
						<head>Workflows</head>
						<p>Partners use different systems, some of which are data-centric and use
							personal database systems, spreadsheets or similar environments. In
							these cases, DEPCHA provides a method for converting data into RDF
							format using a CSV template and a Python script using RDFlib. Python's
							adaptability benefits the transformation process, as historical
							information structures and representations vary from project to project
							depending on research needs. Metadata for the dataset can also be
							included using a simple JSON template. This process is collectively
							referred to as the "dataset" workflow.</p>
						<p>For other partners, such as editors, the aim is to develop a digital
							edition that requires all information to be expressed in XML/TEI format.
							This is particularly valuable for historians seeking contextual
							information, as the digital edition allows for the addition of
							additional layers of information beyond digital facsimiles,
							transcriptions or critical editions. The semantic layer of the
							Bookkeeping Ontology is expressed through additional annotations. This
							is referred to as the "edition" workflow. A comprehensive tutorial for
							different annotation scenarios in XML/TEI has been developed and can be
							accessed via the following link: <ref
							target="https://gams.uni-graz.at/o:depcha.tutorial#xml_tei"
							>https://gams.uni-graz.at/o:depcha.tutorial#xml_tei</ref>.</p>
						<p> Whatever the scenario, there are different requirements from datasets to
							digital editions, but they all share a common feature, which is the
							structure of transactions expressed using the Bookkeeping Ontology and
							formalised as RDF. While datasets consist of RDF data only, the digital
							edition includes both XML/TEI and RDF data. </p>
					</div>
					<div>
						<head>Partners</head>
						<list>
							<item>Kathryn Tomasek, Wheaton College</item>
							<item>Jennifer Stertzer, Center for Digital Editing</item>
							<item>Erica Cavanaugh, Center for Digital Editing</item>
							<item>Ben Brumfield, Brumfield Labs</item>
							<item>Sara Brumfield, Brumfield Labs</item>
							<item>Anna Agbe-Davies, University of North Carolina at Chapel
								Hill</item>
							<item>Jodi Eastberg, Alverno College</item>
							<item>Naoki Kokaze, Chiba University</item>
							<item>Hadewijch Masure, Stadsarchief Leuven</item>
							<item>Michał Schmidt, Warsaw</item>
							<item>Michał Slomski, Warsaw</item>
							<item>Anton Büchel</item>
							<item>Laura Morreale</item>
							<item>Nathan Daniels</item>
							<item>Gabriel Viehhauser, Universität Stuttgart</item>
						</list>
					</div>
					<div>
						<head>Publications and Talks</head>
						<list>
							<item> <ref
								target="https://chpollin.github.io/paper/Pollin_MA_2020_Geschichte.pdf"
								>Pollin C.: Digitale, formale Methoden und Modelle in den
								Geschichtswissenschaften. Am Beispiel digital editierter
								historischer Rechnungsbücher, Master Thesis. Graz. 2020.</ref> </item>
							<item> <ref target="https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2532/paper1.pdf">Pollin C.:
								Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative for Historical Accounts and
								the Bookkeeping Ontology. In: Proceedings of the Doctoral Symposium
								on Research on OnlineDatabases in History (RODBH 2019) Leipzig.
								2019.</ref> </item>
						</list>
						<list>
							<item> <ref
								target="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1CKX9n_kje3jX4q35ryAweL4KeYG2LUCXN2UrMThtM4U/edit#slide=id.gcbe598737f_0_0"
								>Pollin C.: Mapping Semantic Constructs in Historical Domains to
								Visual Structures as Basis for Resource Discovery Using the Example
								of Historical Financial Records. Data for History Conference 2021,
								Berlin. Recording. 30.07.2021. </ref>. <ref
								target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mL43KOMBCJc"
								>Recording</ref>. </item>
							<item> <ref
								target="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1tOW9FhI6elOQDSYCfZanI5Zqc8A5mXL0F8CfsgEtzyw/edit"
								>Pollin C.: “Dashboardfizierung” Historischer Rechnungsbücher.
								Ontologiebasierte Informationsvisualisierung für historische Daten.
								DH-Kolloquium BBAW. 07.05.2021.</ref> </item>
							<item> <ref
								target="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1X5Ul4Uh-KgoH58JSg2MStBMapBZQ7toAccGPrXVszfA/edit"
								>Pollin C.: Modellierung historischer Rechnungsbücher: DEPCHA.
								DH-Kolloquium Uni Köln. Screencast. 22.04.2021.</ref>. <ref
								target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Dsyyhn4iAaY"
								>Screencast</ref> </item>
							<item> <ref
								target="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1-EOOyaMZog6YdYZJ4JMXVqWuTyOEz7uXx-a8Q619-TY/edit#slide=id.g5d67d6e33e_1_0"
								>Pollin C. / Tomasek K.: Making Linkable Data from Account Books:
								Bookkeeping Ontology in the Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative
								for Historical Accounts, TEI Conference 2019, Graz.
								18.11.2019.</ref> </item>
							<item> <ref
								target="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1sO90-1EdHZSGbjGM1MCGeplwbKFlEAL67y5jsYsfw-Y/edit#slide=id.g52707839b8_0_0"
								>Pollin C.: Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative for Historical
								Accounts and the Bookkeeping Ontology. Doctoral Symposium on
								Research on Online Databases in History Leipzig. 04.04.2019.</ref>
							</item>
						</list>
					</div>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back/>
	</text>
</TEI>
